Mansfield Organ Pipe Works Records 1986.0005
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Mansfield Organ Pipe Works Records
undated, 1881-1934
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1986.0005
4 Linear Feet
The Mansfield Organ Pipe Works remained the sole manufacturer of metal-toed organ pipe feet in the world until around 1979. The company traces its origins to Erastus McCollum and his sons Julian and Henry.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
The records were given to the University of Connecticut in 1986.
Arrangement
The collection 1881-1934 is divided into two series:
Series I: Business Records (undated, 1881-1907) contains Printed Materials (advertising and product description in the form of catalogues, brochures, flyers, and price lists), Legal and Financial Documents (contracts, accounts, and records of transactions), Correspondence (correspondence carried on with other organ builders, as well as orders for materials, tools, and equipment),
Orders (containing actual lists of parts yielding specific information about kinds, sizes, and quantities of materials available and in use at the time), Credit Ratings, Bills, Receipts, and Rockville National Bank (cash receipts 1887- 1900), and bank deposit record books (1893-1901).
Series II: Personal Papers (undated, 1886-1934) provide an interesting counterpoint to the business records. Section one, Accounts, contains McCollum household and personal shopping lists and bills. Section two, Letters, includes various notices, invitations, and letters. Section three, Children's, consists of one folder of drawings and stories written by and for children.
History
The Mansfield Organ Pipe Works remained the sole manufacturer of metal-toed organ pipe feet in the world until around 1979, when the process was taken over by the Organ Supply Company of Erie, Pennsylvania.
The company traces its origins to Erastus McCollum and his sons Julian and Henry. Along with Selcon McCollum, Erastus' brother, they built a church organ in their barn in Rockville, Connecticut. Parts, including both wood and metal pipes, were turned out in Erastus' workroom. By 1821, they were advertising as organ builders and rebuilders in the Hartford directory. Their largest accomplishment was the Brewster Hall organ in New Haven in 1850.
Later, the firm known as McCollum Brothers, began to specialize in making wooden pipes and other wooden organ parts such as stoppers, trackers, rack pins, and pipe feet. Probably no complete organs were made by the company after 1850, for Boston and New York had taken over that end of the industry. By 1871, they had moved to Mansfield Depot, Connecticut, and become the Mansfield Organ Pipe Works.
Fenelon C. McCollum, a cousin, managed the company from 1889 until 1925. It was he who invented the metal-toed wooden pipe foot and patented it in 1890. At that time, the firm, employing twenty workers, developed mass production techniques and patented many improvements. After the 1920s, the company specialized still further by making only pipe feet and small organ parts.
Custodial History
The collection was given to the Mansfield Historical Society in 1985 by the McCollum family.
Scope and Content
This small collection is of interest as it provides insights into not only local history and social relationships, but business development in Eastern Connecticut as well. It is of special interest to the music historian since it reveals the detail and scope of the organ manufacturing industry in the area. There is specific information about organs and organ parts; their kind, size, manufacture, function, use, and material composition. For the social scientist or the business historian, the business transactions reveal interpersonal relationships and business enterprise, including employment concerns, complaints about products and services, methods of introducing new processes and products, and availability of goods and services. For the art historian there are many fine examples of letterheads typical of the period. Some materials are water damaged and stained, but legible.
Catalogs; Organ pipes; Organ (Musical instrument); Connecticut (state); Mansfield Depot (inhabited place); Rockville (Conn.); Correspondence; Publications (documents); Administrative records; Financial Records; Fliers (printed matter); Advertisements; McCollum, Erastus; McCollum, Henry; McCollum Family; McCollum, Julian; McCollum, Seldon
- Series I: Business Records, undated, 1881-1907
  - Printed Material, undated, 1897-1898 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Documents, 1882-1927 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence
    - undated, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1882 January - February (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1882 March - June (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1882 July - August (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1882 September - October (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1882 November - December (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1883 - 1885 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1886 January - April (and no month) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1886 May - August (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1886 September - December (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1887 January - March (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 1887 April - June (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 1887 July - September (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 1887 October - December (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 1888 January - April (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1888 May - August (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - 1888 September - December (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - 1889 January - April (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - 1889 May - August (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - 1889 September - December (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - 1891-1895 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - 1896 January - December (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - 1897 January - December (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - 1898-1899 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - 1901 January - December (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - 1902 January - June (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - 1902 July - December (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - 1903 January - October (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - 1904 - 1906 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Orders
    - undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - 1882 January - December (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - 1886-1889 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - 1894-1898 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - 1901 February - December (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - 1902 January - December (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - 1903 January - November (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - 1904-1905 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Credit Ratings, 1882-1903 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Bills, 1882-1888 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Bills, 1891-1893 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Bills, 1894-1895 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Bills, 1896-1907 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Receipts, 1882, 1887-1888 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Receipts, 1891-1902 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Receipts—Groceries, 1887-1894 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Rockville National Bank, 1887-1901 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - 6" Pipe Organ (sample), undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Insurance policy, 1906 (Box OS)
- Series II: Personal Papers, undated, 1886-1934
  - Correspondence, 1887-1934 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Children's drawings, undated (Box 4, Folder 51, Box OS)
  - Accounts, undated, 1886-1893 (Box 4, Folder 52)